盗版电影
Bootleg copies of movies.
就是那种“你总不会去偷车吧”之类的公益广告里天天警告我们的玩意儿
The ones they warned us about from, like, you wouldn't download a piracy or whatever.
基本上就是电影的非官方发行版，而且我先声明啊，我本人可不搞盗版
These are essentially unofficially released versions of films and, full disclosure, I don't pirate anything.
我这么说可不是为了讨好B站申鹤
And I'm not just saying that for YouTube's sake.
我是真不怎么看电视，反正我想看的东西总有正规渠道
I mean, I don't really watch actual TV and I can only access the stuff I want to watch anyway.
而且我现在基本只看B站
And still, I only really watch YouTube,
这玩意儿本来就是免费的，但我还是想聊聊盗版电影这东西
which is free anyway. But I still want to take a look at bootleg copies of movies.
尤其是盗版DVD
Specifically, bootleg DVDs,
多亏了互联网，这玩意儿现在基本已经凉透了
which are pretty much dead thanks to the internet
因为盗版DVD你好歹还得花钱买
because you'd still have to pay for a bootleg DVD,
只是比正版便宜很多而已
just a lot less than a normal DVD.
但只要你在网上那些犄角旮旯里逛逛，你甚至一分钱都不用花
But just by looking around sketchy parts of the internet, you won't have to pay.
然后顺便给电脑安上五十个该死的病毒
And you'll also install 50 fucking viruses.
话说回来，我手里还真有几张这种盘
Now, I own a couple of these.
怎么没有古迦奥特曼
澄清一下，我可不是什么律师，我就是个做卡通视频的油管博主
Now, to clarify, I'm no lawyer who could have guessed I make YouTube videos about cartoons and stuff.
但我觉得我持有这些玩意儿，严格来说应该不算犯法吧，毕竟，我也是受害者啊
But I don't think it's technically illegal for me to own these. I mean, I'm a victim here.
当初我买这些盘的时候，商家可是当正品卖给我的
When I bought all these, I was sold them as if they were perfectly real.
我哪知道这是假的，你看这包装，简直天衣无缝嘛
How was I supposed to know this is fake? Looks perfectly legitimate to me.
不过我是不能卖这些盘的
I can't sell these though,
因为那就成了销售盗版产品了，所以这些玩意儿就只能砸我手里了
because then I'm selling a bootleg product, so I'm stuck with these now.
行了，我们来看看盗版拷贝的种类，先从“枪版”说起
Anyway, now on to the types of pirate copies, starting with cam copies.
想干嘛就干嘛，因为海盗是自由的，你就是个海盗！
Do what you want because a pirate is free! You are a pirate!
这玩意儿可以说是最“非官方”的版本了
These are about as unofficial as they get.
枪版的基本操作就是，一个哥们儿或者姐们儿
The basic concept of a camera if he's a guy or girl,
犯罪不分性别嘛，溜进电影院，再偷带一个破摄像机
which is a gender-neutral crime, goes into a movie theatre and sneaks in a shitty camcorder,
然后想办法藏起来，按下录制键
then hides it somehow and hits record.
搞定，他现在就有了一份属于自己的《鲨鱼黑帮》拷贝了
Boom! Now he has his very own copy of Shark Tale.
但要说这玩意儿是看电影的好方式，那绝对是扯淡
Now, while these are all a good way to watch a movie, fucking no.
不过说实话，这玩意儿还真有种别样的魅力
But, I can't lie, there is sort of a charm to these.
你能听到观众的现场反应，体验到一种你可能从未在影院感受过的氛围
You get to hear the audience reactions to a movie you might have never been able to experience in theatres.
或者见证人们第一次看到那些如今已是名场面时的反应
Or witness people's first reactions to now famous movie scenes.
更别提那种背德感了，天呐，这家伙随时都可能被抓包
Not to mention the thrill of knowing, ooh, this guy could be caught at any moment.
而当他真的被抓时……
And when it does happen...
顶级智斗
Breathtaking.
我记得我只有两次看枪版的经历
Now, I only had two experiences I can remember with cam copies.
那是我在土耳其之类的地方度假的时候
And that's when I was on vacation somewhere like Turkey.
我也不确定是不是土耳其
I don't know if it was Turkey.
但反正是个类似的地方
But it was somewhere like that.
当时有小贩在卖还没上映的电影DVD
And there was guys selling DVDs of movies that weren't out yet.
我的天呐
Oh my god!
太带派了
This is crazy!
我当时还以为这些电影在我们那儿已经出DVD了
These movies must have already come out on DVD here.
于是我买了2016版的《超能敢死队》和《冰川时代5：星际碰撞》
So I bought Ghostbusters 2016 and Ice Age Collision Course.
结果都是些画质烂到没法看的枪版
And they were shitty cam copies that were unwatchable.
我现在已经没留着了，你说我留着那玩意儿干嘛呢
I don't have them anymore because why would I keep them?
不过它们都装在这样的套子里，看起来大概是这个样子
But they came in a sleeve like this and sort of looked like this.
是啊，用这种方式看电影体验很差，但是……
Yeah, this isn't a good way to experience these movies, but...
这两部电影真的有好的欣赏方式吗
Is there even a good way to experience these movies?
大概没有吧
Probably not.
那么，这些人是怎么被抓到的呢
Now, how do these people get caught?
嗯，一些电影院开始给员工发奖金
Well, some movie theatres have begun offering rewards to employees
只要他们能抓住录制电影的人就给钱
who are able to catch people recording movies.
比如一千英镑
Things like £1000,
这很可能会让更多偷录的人被抓
which is likely going to increase the amount of people caught
从电影院的角度来看这很合理
and make sense from a movie theatre's perspective.
如果网上有免费的电影可以看，他们还怎么卖票呢
If there's a free version of the movie they're charging you to see online,
谁还会花钱去看呢
why would people pay to see it?
所以他们会损失一大笔钱
So they'll lose a lot of money.
因此花一小笔钱来阻止这种行为是完全说得通的
So spending a tiny bit of money in comparison to try and stop it makes sense.
还有一种方法是在银幕上加上隐藏的圆点图案，每个影院的图案都不同
There's also hidden patterns of dots on the screens that differ from theatre to theatre,
这样通过观察这些圆点，就能知道某个枪版是从哪个电影院流出来的
so that you'd be able to see which movie theatre a camcopy came from by looking at these dots.
这些圆点通常是看不见的，但如果你知道它们在哪以及如何找到它们
You wouldn't usually be able to see these, but if you knew where they were and how to find them,
那你就能找到是哪家影院了
then you'd be able to find the theatre.
有些影院还配备了夜视技术，专门用来在黑暗中抓偷录的人
Some theatres also have night vision technology to catch people recording in the dark.
所以总结一下枪版，基本上就是有人在电影院里录电影
So camcopies, to sum it up, are basically someone recording the movie in the theatre
还得把摄像机藏起来，结果就是画质烂得像坨翔，画面裁剪得乱七八糟
and hiding the camera which results in dogshit quality, poorly cropped footage,
音质也差到爆，因为用的就是摄像机自带的麦克风
terrible audio since it's just using the camera's mic,
还有观众的噪音，甚至可能有人影晃动
audience noise, potential silhouette,
总之，这不是看电影的好方式
and yeah, this isn't a good way to watch a movie.
接下来，我们来看看TS版
Moving on, we also have Telesync.
你就是个海盗
You are a pirate!
TS版的质量比枪版要好得多
Telesyncs are much better quality than camcopies.
首先，准枪版的音频是直接从声源录制的
For starters, a Telesync is recorded with a direct connection to a sound source,
也就是说音频不是通过影院里的麦克风录的
meaning the audio isn't being recorded through a microphone in the theatre,
而是直接从源头录制，这样不仅音质更高
it's just being recorded straight from the source which won't just make it higher quality,
还能消除任何观众的噪音
but will also get rid of any audience noise.
TS版通常还会用更好的摄像机和三脚架
Telesync are also usually recorded with a better camera on a tripod,
而且是在放映室里录的，这意味着拍摄角度会更好
in the actual projection booth itself, meaning the angle will be better
不会有糟糕的裁剪或者挡在前面的人影
and there won't be bad cropping or silhouette of people in the way,
但这也意味着很可能是影院员工干的
but also means it will likely be done by an employee at the theatre,
所以风险要大得多，因为一旦被抓，他们就会丢掉工作
so it's a much higher risk, because if they get caught, they'll lose their job,
这对他们未来的职业生涯可不是什么好事
and that won't be a great look for them in the future.
摄像机的设置通常也会被调整，以每秒24帧的速度拍摄
The camera settings are also usually altered so that it shoots in 24 frames per second,
这样就和电影的帧率匹配了，曝光之类的参数也会调好
like how the film would be running, so they match, and the exposure on all the cameras,
总之效果会更好，这里是枪版和TS版的对比
but that would be better. Here's a comparison between a cam and telesync.
接下来是胶片转录版
Now next up is a Telecine.
想干嘛就干嘛，海盗的生活就是这么潇洒，你就是个海盗
Do what you want, that's a pirate that's free! You are a pirate!
这基本上就是有人用这种胶片转录机来复制电影胶片
Which is essentially when someone makes a copy of the actual film using one of these telesyn machines.
这种是质量最好的版本，基本上和你买的DVD没啥区别
These are like, the best quality ones, and are basically the same as what you'd see on a DVD,
因为它本质上就是对电影胶片的直接拷贝
since it is basically just a copy of the actual film.
然而，这种版本极其罕见，因为要制作胶片转录版
However, these are incredibly rare, due to the fact that to actually get a Telecine copy,
盗版贩子需要搞到一份电影胶片，还有一台胶片转录机
the bootleggers would need a copy of the film, and also a Telecine machine,
说实话，这两样东西都挺难弄到手的
which, I mean, both those things are quite hard to come by.
所以大多数时候，盗版贩子会选择其他方式
And so most of the time, bootleggers opt for one of the other options.
还有一种叫“工作样片”，就是电影的未完成草稿版
There's also work prints, which is like, a rough unfinished version of the film,
通常屏幕上会有时间码和水印之类的东西
generally with stuff like times and watermarks on the screen.
你们知道吗，那部还没上映的痞老板大电影，整个都在推特上泄露了
You know how the entire Plankton movie that's not out yet leaked on Twitter?
对，那就是工作样片，我一帧画面都不会给你们看的
Yeah, that's a work print, and I'm not gonna show a single frame,
因为维亚康姆（Viacom）肯定会把我的频道给炸了
because Viacom would absolutely nuke my channel.
这种泄露极其罕见，不常发生
These are ultra shiny rare, and don't happen often.
不过连续两部海绵宝宝电影在上映前都发生了这种事
Happened to two Spongebob movies in a row before they came out though.
另外，据说《鼠国流浪记》有一个早期版本
Also, supposedly, there's an early version of Flushed Away,
里面有两个被从正片中剪掉的老鼠管家角色
featuring two Rat Butler guys that are cut from the film,
这个版本曾以《鼠国流浪记2》的名义在盗版DVD上发行
which was released on bootleg DVDs as Flushed Away 2.
只是想提一下，虽然这个版本现在已经失传了，但还是挺有意思的
Just wanted to mention that, I mean, it is lost right now, but still.
现在我们来说说直接从DVD翻录的版本
Now we get to straight up rips of DVDs.
比如我手上这张《人生遥控器》，它和正版的没任何区别
Like, I have one of Click, and it's just the same as a normal Click DVD.
哦，是吗
Hmm, oh really?
这些和正版DVD一模一样，但价格会更便宜
These are just the same as normal DVDs, but they'd be cheaper.
不过现在这都不重要了
That doesn't matter now.
看来我只能把这张盘加到我那堆积如山的《人生遥控器》DVD收藏里了
Guess I'll just add this Click to the ever-growing pile of Click DVDs.
好了，盗版DVD的种类就介绍到这里
Anyway, that covers the types of bootleg DVDs.
现在，我觉得聊聊盗版贩子被抓的案例会很有趣
Now, I thought it'd be interesting to go over instances where bootleggers were caught.
首先来看一个来自底特律WXYZ-TV第七频道的视频
Starting off with a video from WXYZ-TV Detroit Channel 7,
标题是
titled,
《盗版贩子在本地电影院被抓》
Bootleggers Caught at a Local Movie Theater.
这是一则新闻报道，内容嘛，就是
Which is a news report about, well,
盗版贩子在本地电影院被抓了
bootleggers being caught at a local movie theater.
这件事发生在密歇根州克林顿镇的一家星光影院
So this happened at a Star Theater in Clinton Township, Michigan,
当时有两个家伙试图偷录一部电影
where there were two guys trying to film a movie.
他们当场被抓，这让我们能清楚地看到他们的作案工具
They were caught while doing it, and this gives us a pretty good look at their setup here.
他们用的是一台索尼摄像机
They were using a Sony camcorder.
我不是什么摄像机专家，但据我判断
Now, I'm no camera expert, but from what I can tell,
看起来像是这款，索尼HDR-CX430V
it appears to be this camera, the Sony HDR-CX430V
高清闪存手持摄像机
High Definition Flash Memory Handycam Camcorder,
这款摄像机是在2013年1月发布的
which was released back in January 2013,
so it makes sense with this news report being released in October 2013.
而这则新闻报道是2013年10月的，所以时间上对得上
不过要是有说错的，欢迎指正
But feel free to correct me.
总之，他们用这个夹子把摄像机固定在影院座位的扶手上
Anyway, they had this clamp here that they used to attach it onto the armrest of the theater seats.
固定好之后，他们用一条毛巾盖住，以免被发现
Once that was set up, they covered it with a towel so they couldn't get caught.
虽然最后还是被抓了，但想法是好的
I mean, it didn't work, but still.
他们当时试图偷录的电影是2013年的《地心引力》
The specific movie they were attempting to film was the 2013 movie Gravity.
这两个家伙之所以被抓，多亏了我们前面提到的隐藏水印
Now, the way these fellas got caught was thanks to the previously mentioned hidden watermarks
通过这些水印，人们追踪到了他们之前一些盗版电影的确切拍摄影院
that were used to track down the exact theater that some of their previous bootlegs were filmed at.
于是，一名私家侦探被派往该影院，并成功抓住了他们
So, a private investigator was sent to the theater and was able to catch them.
我没查到这两个人最后到底怎么样了
Now, I can't find what ended up happening to these specific guys,
但新闻报道确实给了我们一些线索，让我们能猜到他们的下场
but the news report does give us a little insight as to what might have happened.
看好了
Boom!
初犯的话，要罚款一万美元，外加一年监禁
So for a first offence, it'd be a $10,000 fine and one year in jail.
再犯的话罚金和刑期翻倍，三进宫的话再翻倍
Then it doubles for second offence and dubs again for third offence.
所以，下场不咋地
So, not great.
不管怎样，这两个家伙是把电影传到网上的
Anyway, these guys were posting these movies online.
那么，我们来看看卖盗版DVD的案例怎么样
So, how about we look at someone selling bootleg DVDs?
想干嘛就干嘛，因为海盗是自由的
Do what you want, cause the pirate is free!
这件事发生在2011年的佛罗里达州波尔克县
This event took place in 2011 and happened in Polk County, Florida.
这背后涉及一个完整的犯罪团伙，警方查获了八千张盗版DVD
There was a whole crime ring involved here and 8,000 bootleg DVDs were found.
我们能看到一些照片，让我们得以一窥他们幕后的操作
We get to see some photos that give us a behind the scenes look at the operation here.
第一张图只是一堆盗版DVD，据说当时售价是正版DVD的一半
Our first image simply shows a stack of bootleg DVDs that were apparently being sold for half the price of regular DVDs at the time.
第二张图显示了他们成堆的同款电影，所以我们能看到他们当时在卖些什么
Our second image shows there's stacks of the same movie, so we can see some of the stuff they were selling.
这里有《里约大冒险》，这里是《绿灯侠》，那边还有《惊声尖叫》等等
We have Rio here, Green Lantern here, Scream there and many more.
我们还有一张最有趣的图片，由于某种原因，感觉像是那个
We also have the most interesting image, which for some reason seems to be taken
在网上爆料《任天堂明星大乱斗》的哥们儿拍的，因为实在是太糊了
by the same guy who posted Smash Bros. leaks online because it's really blurry.
但我们还是能看到这边堆着一摞摞的电影盒和封套
But we can actually see stacks of cases and sleeves for movies over here
还有那边一大堆准备刻录的空白DVD
along with a shit ton of blank DVDs ready to have movies burnt to them over here.
而且，这些家伙以每张大约一美元的价格买入这些DVD
Also, these guys were buying these DVDs for like a dollar each
然后在亚马逊和eBay上当正品卖
and selling them on Amazon and eBay as legit.
从而赚取了巨额利润，每周高达两万美金，哎我曹乐
Thus making a load of money, up to 20 grand a week, god damn.
他们总共从中获利五十万美元
They in total made half a million dollars from this.
现在，如果我告诉你盗版DVD其实还没死透，你会怎么想
Now, what if I told you that bootleg DVDs aren't actually a dead thing?
你可能会惊讶，但也可能不会
You might be surprised, but also maybe not.
如今的情况有点不同
It's a little different nowadays
很多盗版只是发行一些从未有过DVD版本的东西，还有一些是VHS录像带的转录
with lots of them just being releases of things that never actually had DVD releases and also some of VHS releases.
但大多数时候，买这些东西的人完全知道它们不是正品
But most of the time people buying these are fully aware they're not real.
更多的是他们只是想拥有这些东西的实体版而已
It's more that they just want to own a physical version of some of these.
就好像，没人会买一盘《地狱客栈》的录像带
Like, no one is buying a has-been-hotel VHS
还以为这是亚马逊百分百官方正品吧
thinking it's a 100% official Amazon product.
但有时候盗版DVD还是会被当成正品来卖
But sometimes bootleg DVDs are sold as legitimate,
就像我在一个视频里看到的这些《开心汉堡店》的DVD
like these Bob's Berkus DVDs I saw in a video.
不过比起当年，现在这个问题已经小很多了
It's still a much smaller problem than it was back then though.
总之，感谢推特账号“Theater Bootleg Archives”
Anyway, thanks to the Twitter account Theater Bootleg Archives,
他们也有个油管频道，你应该去订阅一下
they also have a YouTube channel you should sub to.
这个视频很棒，我们关于盗版DVD世界的探险也差不多该结束了
This video is great, and that about wraps up our adventure into the world of bootleg DVDs.
了解了背后的故事后，看看这些东西还挺有意思的
These things are cool to look at knowing the story behind them, but
但随着互联网的普及，这门手艺已经几近失传
they're an almost dead art at this point with the internet existing.
用这种方式看电影体验极差，我想没人会喜欢看这种东西，但是
They're a terrible way to watch a movie, I don't think anyone enjoys watching these, but...
如果你想在《龙凤双胞》还在影院上映时就在家看，那你也只能将就了
If you wanted to watch Jack and Jill at home before it finished its theatrical run, you'd have to settle.
另外，你为啥要看那玩意儿，你有毛病吗
Also, why? What's wrong with you?
总之，快去看《沙雕校园》
Anyway, watch our stupid school.
这是我制作的节目，我也在里面，看，这是它的枪版
It's a show I made, and I'm in. Look, here's a cam copy of it.